Guide to the Luis Leal Papers, 1946-1985
Department of Special Collections
- Series 2: Manuscripts of major works
  - Subseries C: Unpublished (as far as we know) manuscripts by authors and researchers: (Not Luis Leal)
    - (These are names that did not appear on original Luis Leal folder, but, belongs to unpublished manuscripts by authors and researchers. They were together with the rest on Box D-23). Martha P. Francescato, " A New approach to three novels by Carlos Fuentes: The malaise of time". (research materials). The figure of La malinche in the texts of Elena Garro, Sandra Cypess. Sandra Cypess. Valoracion, Luis González Obregon. "La Función de la naturaleza en canciones para cantar en las barras", Andrew P. Debicki. "La naturaleza en las Canciones de Gorostiza", Andrew P. Debicki. (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - (These are names that did not appear on original Luis Leal folder, but, belongs to unpublished manuscripts by authors and researchers. They were together with the rest on Box D-23). Harley D. Oberhelman, editing the uncollected works of Manuel Gutiérrez Nájera. (reasearch materials). Memorias de Pancho Villa: Villa and the spaniards, By Guillermo Rojas. Fuentes populares en Memorias de Pancho Villa, Mark Cramer. Texto y contexto de Los poeminimos de Efrain Huería, Guillermo Villarreal. Azuela, Mariano (1873-1952). Biografía. Francisco Monterde. (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - (These are names that did not appear on original Luis Leal folder, but, belongs to unpublished manuscripts by authors and researchers. They were together with the rest on Box D-23). "La Mano del comandante Aranda", de Alfonso Reyes. Sam L. Slick. José Revueltas: El hombre y su obra literaria. Margaret L. Snook: Lugar y espacio en El amor en los tiempos de cólera. Margaret L. Snook: The motif of voyage as mythical symbol in El amor en los tiempos de cólera, by Gabriel Garcia Márquez. Margaret L. Snook: The Power Struggle: Gender and Voice in "Moscas y arenas" by Bioy Casares. Francisco Monterde: Calderon, Fernando (1809-1845). Biografía. José Rojas Carcidueñas: Alaman, Lucas (1792-1853). Biografía. Valoración. Salado Alvarez. Valoración. Amado Nervo. (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - (These are names that did not appear on original Luis Leal folder, but, belongs to unpublished manuscripts by authors and researchers. They were together with the rest on Box D-23). Inés Arredondo: Orozco y Berra, Manuel (1816-1881). Biografía. O. Z.: Tumba clandestina. Susan Levine: "The lesson of the Quijote" in the works of Carlos Fuentes and Juan Coytisolo. J. S. Brushwood:Heriberto Frías on social behavior and redemptive woman. Lee Ann Grace: El periquillo sarniento and linguistic realism in the picaresque. Fernandez de Lizardi and Cervantes, by John Skirius. (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Series 3: Manuscripts of articles, lectures, presentations
  - Subseries A: Luis Leal, unpublished articles and books review in press
    - (Folder of unclassified, unidentified parts of manuscripts by Luis Leal). Miguel Angel Menéndez (1905-1982). Islas Marías, novela - drama - guión El Cuento fantástico y el cuento de realismo mágico: convergencias y divergencias. (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - (Folder of unclassified, unidentified parts of manuscripts by Luis Leal). Mariano Azuela: Precursor de los nuevos novelistas. Agustín Yáñez. Octavio Paz (México, 1914). Carlo Antonio Castro. Siluetas mexicanas. Jalapa: Editorial Amate, 1980. Quixotico Scriptures:Essays on the textuality of hispanic literature by Elias L. Rivers. Bloomingto, Indiana University Press, 1984. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: Luis Leal, unpublished articles
    - León Hebreo. (15 pp.) La Gitanilla y Pedro de Urdemalas. (7 pp.) Mr. Karnis' article on the need of translations of Latin American plays.... (2 pp.) D'Annunzio y Valle Inclán. (5 pp.) El origen de un incidente. Del Persilis y Sigismunda de Cervantes. (6 pp.) Pier delle Vigne. (5 pp.) Dante and Boniface VIII. (4 pp.) Dante's behavior in the presence of Beatrice. (5 pp.) Contributions of the mexican people to our american heritage. (10 pp.) Los norteamericanos en los corridos mexicanos. (8 pp.) La educación en México. (4 pp.) La educación en el México precortesiano. (7 pp.) (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - La educación en México en la epoca colonial. (6 pp.) La educación durante la epoca de la independencia. (5. pp.) La epoca moderna. (7 pp.) The faith of Columbus. (7 pp.) La suerte de Colón. (3 pp.) Contemporary themes in mexican literature. (30 pp.) Foreign languages and the minorities. (7 pp.) Contributors of the new latin american novel to world literature. (17 pp.) (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - The originality of latin american culture. (18 pp.) Elementos narrativos en el Ulises Criollo de José Vasconcelos. (10 pp.) Octavio Paz: North and South. (7 pp.) La actividad crítica latinoamericana en los Estados Unidos y el Canadá. (20 pp.) Mexico today. (20 pp.) México. (14 pp.) The mexican writer and the economic crisis. (6 pp.) Mexican literature. Tradition and innovation. (5 pp.) (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - The novel of the Mexican Revolution reconsidered. (9 pp.) Novels of the Revolution. (3 pp.) José Guadalupe Posada. (1852-1913). (1 p.) Carlo Antonio Castro. Siluetas mexicanas. (5 pp.) Observaciones sobre la ponencia de Carlo Monsiváis. (5 pp.) Antimodernismo en la revista Guatemala llustrada. (4 pp.) Foreword to book by Professor Parent. (3 pp.) Ferraro's Goldoni. (6 pp.) Miguel Angel Asturias. (5 pp.) El P. Juan de Tovar. (7 pp.) The contemporary spanish american novel. (8 pp.) Review for New scholar. (3 pp.) The mexican novel before Rulfo. (4 pp.) Mexican women of Mexico. (3 pp.) El sarape de Saltillo. (8 pp.) From history to fiction: The Mexican Revolution in the novels of Mariano Azuela. (15 pp.) (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - La evolución del Confabulario de Juan José Arreola. (5 pp.) El Bestiario de Juan José Arreola. (9 pp.) Releyendo El Zarco. (6 pp.) El tiempo en "Al filo del agua". (3 pp.) El cine y la revolución. (5 pp.) El compadre Mendoza. (3 pp.) Aspects of mexican booklore. (5 pp.) Rulfo and the mexican short story. (12 pp.) La técnica del monólogo interior. (32 pp.) El género "cuento" y la crítica literaria. (3 pp.) El español de Pirandello. (5 pp.) Fernando Alegría, homenaje. (5 pp.) Darío. El oro de Mallorca. (5 pp.) La realidad anulada: "El desayuno", cuento de Amparo Dávila. (5 pp.) The originality of latin american culture. (17 pp.) (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - A manera de prólogo. (6 pp.) The new latin american novel: A Profile. (18 pp.) El Barroco en hispanoamerica. (2 pp.) El studio de la literatura hispanoamericana: Selección de temas y métodos de trabajo. (2 pp.) Madero. (20 pp.) Micros. (3 pp.) Luis de la Rosa. (8 pp.) El catálogo de palabras mayas de Carrillo y Ancona. (4 pp.) Recordando a Pirandello. (2 pp.) Historia y ficción en la narrativa de José Vasconcelos. (13 pp.) Villaurutia y Gamboa. (3 pp.) Un cuento de Carlos Fuentes. (5 pp.) Fernán González de Eslava. (4 pp.) Martín Luis Guzmán - El aguila y la serpiente. (4 pp.) Guzmán, Martín Luis. (6 pp.) Realismo mágico. (8 pp.) Impact of the Mexican Revolution upon life and letters. (5 pp.). incomplete La enseñanza de la literatura Iberoamericana. (4 pp.). MS & TS La poesía mexicana en la Antología de J. M. Cohen. (6 pp.) A manera de Prólogo (for cuadernos americanos). (6 pp.) (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Subseries C: Luis Leal, unpublished lectures
    - (Numbers refer to Luis Leal, A Bibliography...) #344a - "Aspects of contemporary mexican literature." 58th Annual Winter Conference, University of Northern Colorado, Greeley, Colorado, 30 Jan. 1986. #367a - "El cuento fantástico y el cuento de realismo mágico. Convergencias y divergencias." Morelia, Michoacán, México, Instituto Michoacano de Cultura, 6 Aug. 1987. #418 - "La literatura del '68." Yale University, New Haven, Conn. 7 Nov. 1981. #421 - "Lo real maravilloso." University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah, 5 Dec. 1985. (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - (Numbers refer to Luis Leal, A Bibliography...) #441 - "New world picaresque." Forum Romanicum. University of Illinois, Urbana. 24 Feb. 1975. #443 - "La novela de la Revolución Mexicana." Howard University, Washington, D.C. 2 May 1968. #489 - "Spanish american picaresque literature: From Oquendo to Lizardi." Syracuse University, Syracuse, New York. 1 May 1971. #491 - "The spanish language in Mexico." University of Georgia, Atlanta Campus. 25 Sept 1956. (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - (Numbers refer to Luis Leal, A Bibliography...) #494 - "La técnica del cuento." Casa de la Cultura, Guadalajara, Jalisco, México. 2 Aug. 1962. #501 - "Vida y costumbres en hispanoamérica." NDEA Institute, Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio. 3 March 1960. (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - (Numbers refer to Luis Leal, A Bibliography...) #385 - "Education in Mexico." Friends of Mexico. Chicago, Illinois. 18 June 1943. #391 - "La enseñanza del español en el México del Siglo XVI." Los directores de programas bilingües, Camarillo, Calif. 30 Nov. 1983. Slide Lecture. #392 - "El escritor mexicano y la crisis económica." Conference on "Is Mexico on its way to recovery?" Business Economics Exchange Program, Dept. of Economics, UCSB. 9 Nov. 1983. #400a - "García Márquez en México." AATSP, Los Angeles, Calif. 16 Aug. 1987. (In honor of Kurt Lexy). #475 - "Review and critique of papers presented at workshop on 'Chicano theory and methods'." California State, Los Angeles, at Pasadena, 14 Dec. 1986. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Subseries D: Luis Leal, unpublished presentations
    - Juan José Arreola. Eduardo Caballero Calderón. (April 5, 1973) Dr. Justino Fernández. Carlos Fuentes. (M ay, 1986) Victor Fuentes (homenaje). (April 20, 1988) Pedro Guillén. Jorge Icaza. Wigberto Jiménez Moreno. Ernesto Mejía Sánchez. Robert G. Mead. Marco Antonio Montes de Oca. (Jan. 13, 1987) Octavio Paz. (April 11, 1986) Gustavo Sainz. (October 16, 1979) Gustavo Sainz. Anibal Sánchez Reulet. Chancellor Uehling. Presentation of ten lithographs for exhibit at the Center for Chicano Studies. To the South Carolina Chapter of the American Association of Teachers of Spanish and Portuguese. Nuevo coloquio sobre la novela (Seminario 41, MLA, Chicago, 1971) (position paper). Santa Barbara Museum of Art presentation. (October 5, 1984) Reception, Baltimore Hotel, Santa Barbara. (October 19, 1984) (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Subseries E: Luis Leal, published books manuscripts
    - Breve historia de la literatura hispanoamericana. (1971) pp. 1-90 (cont...) (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Breve historia de la literatura hispanoamericana. (1971) pp. 91-199 (cont...) (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Breve historia de la literatura hispanoamericana. (1971) pp. 200-325 (cont...) (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Breve historia de la literatura hispanoamericana. (1971) pp. 326-425 (cont...) (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Breve historia de la literatura hispanoamericana. (1971) pp. 426-533 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Breve historia de la literatura hispanoamericana. (1971) Bibliography for above book. (cont...) (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Breve historia de la literatura hispanoamericana. (1971) Bibliography for above book. (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Aztlán y México. (1985) primera parte: AZTLáN. pp. 1-102 (cont...) (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Aztlán y México. (1985) segunda parte: ANAHUAC. pp. 1-94 (cont...) (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Aztlán y México. (1985) En busca de Aztlán y otros estudios. pp. 1-125 (cont...) (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Aztlán y México. (1985) En busca de Aztlán y otros estudios. pp. 126-259 (cont...) (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Aztlán y México. (1985) En busca de Aztlán y otros estudios. pp. 260-363 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Juan Rulfo. (1983) (final) pp. 1-188 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Juan Rulfo. (1983) (1st copy with corrections) pp. 1-149 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Juan Rulfo. (1983) (2nd copy with corrections) pp. 1-163 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Juan Rulfo. (1983) (3rd copy with corrections) pp. 1-101 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Juan Rulfo. (1983) (these are corrections made for chapters 5-8 - extra copies.) (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Juan Rulfo. (1983) (corrections of notes and references for chapters 1-7) (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Juan Rulfo. (1983) (Selected bibliographies and index) (also two copies - drafts) (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Juan Rulfo. Twayne 1983 (page proofs) (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Cuentistas hispanoamericanos del Siglo Veinte. (1972) pp. 1-99 (cont...) (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Cuentistas hispanoamericanos del Siglo Veinte. (1972) pp. 100-199 (cont...) (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Cuentistas hispanoamericanos del Siglo Veinte. (1972) pp. 200-342 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Pedro Páramo. (edition) (1970) pp. 1-89 (cont...) (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Pedro Páramo. (edition) (1970) pp. 90-176 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Historia del cuento hispanoamericano, 1st ed. (1966) (cont...) (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Historia del cuento hispanoamericano, 1st ed. (1966) (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Historia del cuento hispanoamericano, 2nd ed. (1971) (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Leyendas. (1985) (cont...) (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Leyendas. (1985) (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - El cuento veracruzano. (Antología) (1966) (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Cuentos de la Revolución. (1976) (cont...) (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Cuentos de la Revolución. (1976) (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Chicano Literatura - An Overview (with Pepe Barrón, 1982), published in Baker, ed. Three american literatures. (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Mariano Azuela, vida y obra. (1961) pp. 1-119 (cont...) (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Mariano Azuela, Vida y Obra. (1961) pp. 120-217 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Mariano Azuela; Páginas escogidas. (1973) (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Mariano Azuela. (B.A.) (1967) (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Breve historia del cuento mexicano. (first draft) (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Breve historia del cuento mexicano. (1956) (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Parts published & parts unpublished for Breve historia del cuento mexicano. (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Antología del cuento mexicano. (Andrea) (1957) (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Some unpublished chapters for above book. (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Cuento hispanoamericano contemporáneo. (1988) (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Bibliografía del cuento mexicano. (1958) (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - El cuento mexicano: De los orígenes al modernismo. (B.A.) (1966) (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Subseries F: Luis Leal published articles, lectures, etc. (numbers refer to listings in Luis Leal, A Bibliography with Interpretative and Critical Essays. Eds. Salvador Güereña and Raquel Quiroz González. Berkeley: Chicano Studies Library Publications Unit, University of California at Berkeley, 1988).
    - I. Books (chapters or parts): #1 - Aztlán y México: Perfiles literarios e históricos. Binghamton, N.Y.: Bilingual Review Press, 1985. (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - I. Books (chapters or parts): #4 - Breve historia del cuento mexicano. México: Editorial Studium, 1957. (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - I. Books (chapters or parts): #6 - El cuento hispanoamericano. Buenos Aires: Centro Editor de América Latina, 1967. #7 - Historia del cuento hispanoamericano. México: Editorial Studium, 1966, 2nd ed. rev., 1971. (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - I. Books (chapters or parts): #10 - Mariano Azuela. New York: Twayne Publishers, 1971. #12 - México, civilizaciones y culturas. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Co., 1955, 2nd ed. rev., 1971. #13 - Panorama de la iteratura mexicana actual. Washington: Unión Panamericana, 1968. #15 - Teacher's manual for "Siglo Veinte". (with Joseph Silverman). New York: Holt, Renehart & Winston, 1968. (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - II. Anthologies and books edited (chapters or parts): #21 - El cuento veracruzano. Antología. Xalapa: Universidad Veracruzana, 1966. #22 - Cuentos de la Revolución. Biblioteca del Estudiante Universitario: México: UNAM, 1977. #25 - Día de los muertos. Ed. Luis Leal et al. Santa Barbara: Center for Chicano Studies and University Library, 1983. #35 - Siglo veinte. (with Joseph Silverman). New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1968. (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - III. Contributions to books: #38 - "Amado Nervo." Encyclopedia Britannica. 1960 ed. #39 - "Amado Nervo." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1973 ed. #41 - "Arturo Uslar Pietri." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1975 ed. #42 - "La caricia suprema: Contextos de luz y sombra en El águila y la serpiente." Commemorative Series: Five Essays on Martín Luis Gúzman. Riverside: University of California: Latin American Studies Program, 1978, pp. 72-82. #44 - "El Cautiverio feliz y la crónica novelesca." In Prosa hispanoamericana virreinal. Ed. by Raquel Chang-Rodríguez, Barcelona, Spain: Borras Ediciones, 1978, pp. 113-140. #46 - "Contemporary Mexican Novel and Short Story." In Contemporary Latin American Literature. Ed. Harvey L. Johnson and Philip B. Taylor, Jr. Houston, Texas: University of Houston, 1973, pp. 40-47. #47 - "El cuento de ambiente: Luvina de Juan Rulfo." (see No. 144.) #48 - "El cuento de la generación del 80." Commemorative Series on the Centennial of the Argentine Generation. Riverside: University of California: Latin American Studies Program, 1980, pp. 25-45. #49 - "Darío en México." In Studios sobre Ruben Darío. Ed. Ernesto Mejía Sánchez. México: Fondo de Cultura Económica, 1968, pp. 118-124. Rpt. Specialia, 1 Aug. 1970, pp. 46-48. (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - III.Contributions to books: #51 - "La estructura de Pedro Páramo." In Anuario de Letras. Ed. Juan M. Lope Blanch. México: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, 4, (1965), 287-294. Rpt. in Homenaje a Juan Rulfo. Ed. Helmy Giacoman, New York: Anaya-Las Américas, 1974, pp. 13-22. Rpt. in Recopilación de textos sobre Juan Rulfo. Ed. A.B.R. La Habana: Casa de las Américas, 1969, pp. 96-105. Rpt. in La narrativa de Juan Rulfo. Ed. Joseph Sommers. México: Secretaría de Educación Pública, 1974. Rpt. in Para cuando yo me ausente. Ed. Juan Rulfo. México: Editorial Grijalbo, 1983, pp. 257-266. Rpt. in La Semana de Bellas Artes, 146 (1980), pp. 14-15. Rpt. in La Opinión: La Comunidad, No. 286, 12 Jan., 1986, pp. 6-7, 11. #52 - "Felix Varela and Liberal Thought." In The Ibero-American Enlightenment. Ed. A. Owen Aldridge. Urbana, Illinois: University of Illinois Press, 1971, pp. 234-242. (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - III. Contributions to books: #54 - "Guatemala." Encyclopedia Britannica. 1967 ed. #55 - "La hija de los ríos." Commemorative Series on Rómulo Gallegos. Riverside: University of California: Latin American Studies Program, 1979, pp. 99-117. #56- "Historiografía hispanoamericana." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1973 ed. #57 - "History and Myth in Narrative of Carlos Fuentes." In Carlos Fuentes: A critical View. Ed. Robert Brody and Charles Rossman, Austin: University of Texas Press, 1982, pp. 3-17. #58 - "Hugo Wast." Encyclopedia Britannica. 1960 ed. #59 - "Ignacio Rodríguez Galván." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1974 ed. (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - III. Contributions to books: #60 - "Interpretaciones de la literatura mexicana." In Humanitas. Monterrey: Universidad de Nuevo León, 1968, pp. 259-273. (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - III. Contributions to books: #64 - "José Julián Marti." Encyclopedia Britannica. 1965 ed. #65 - "José María de Heredia." Encyclopedia Britannica. 1960 ed. #66 - "José Peón Contreras." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1974 ed. #67 - José Rubén Romero." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1974 ed. #69 - "Juan Rulfo." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1974 ed. #70 - "Juan Rulfo." In Narrativa crítica de nuestra América. Ed. Joaquín Roy. Madrid, Spain: Editorial Castalia, 1978, pp. 258-286. #71 - "La literatura de México." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1973 ed. #72 - "La literatura de Nicaragua." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1973 ed. (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - III. Contributions to books: #73 - "La literatura de Venezuela." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1975 ed. #74 - "La literatura mexicana del diecinueve: en busca de una expresión." In Memoria del Quinceavo Congreso del Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana. Ed. Renato Rosaldo and Robert Anderson. Tucson: University of Arizona, 1974, pp. 169-174. #75 - "La literatura mexicana en siglo XX (1930-1963)." In Panorama das literaturas das Américas. Ed. Joaquim de Montezuma de Carvalho. Angola: Edicao do Municipio de Nova Lisboa, 4, 1963 (1965), pp. 1997-2050. #77 - "Manuel José Othón." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1973 ed. #79 - "Mito a realidad en la invención de América." In The Two Hesperias. Ed. Americo Bugliani. Madrid: José Porrúa Turanzas, 1977, pp. 197-207. (Literary Studies in Honor of Joseph G. Fucilla on the Occasion of his 80th Birthday.) (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - III. Contributions to books: #80 - "Mito y realismo social en Miguel Angel Asturias." In Homenaje a Miguel Angel Asturias. Ed. Helmy F. Giacoman. New York: Las Américas, 1971 (1972), pp. 311-324. (see No. 200). #81 - "El movimiento estridentista." In Memoria del Undecimo Congreso del Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana. México, 1965, pp. 77-87. Rpt. In Los vanguardismos en la America Latina. Ed. Oscar Collazos. La Habana: Casa de las Américas, 1970, pp. 157-166. #82 - "Native and Foreign Influences in Contemporary Mexican Literatur: A Search for Identity." In Tradition and Renewal: Essays on Twentieth-Century Latin American Literature and Culture. Ed. Merlin H. Forster. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1975, pp. 102-128. (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - III. Contributions to books: #83 - "Las Novelas morales de Juan de Piña Izquierdo." In Anuario de Letras. Ed. Juan M. Lope Blanch. México: UNAM, 12 (1974), pp. 221-230. #84 - "La nueva novela hispanoamericana ante la critíca española." In Homenaje a Luis ALberto Sánchez. Ed. Robert Mead et al. Madrid: Insula, 1983, pp. 343-352. #85 - "El nuevo cuento mexicano." In El cuento hispanoamericano ante la crítica. Ed. Enrique Pupo-Walker. Madrid: Editorial Castalia, 1973, pp. 280-295. #86a - "El paraiso recobrado." Commemorative Series: Essays on Hugo Rodríguez-Alcalá. Latin American Studies Program. Riverside: Univ. of California, 1985, pp. 64-73. #87 - "Picaresca hispanoamericana: de Oquendo a Lizardi." In Estudios de literatura hispanoamericana en honor a José J. Arrom. North Carolina Studies in the Romance Languages and Literatures. Ed. Andrew P. Debick, and Enrique Pupo-Walker. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina, Department of Romance Languages, 1974, pp. 47-58. #88 - "Pícaros y léperos en la narrativa mexicana." In La picaresca: orígenes, textos y estructuras. Ed. Manuel Criado de Val. Madrid: Fundación Universitaria Española, 1979, 1979, pp. 1033-1040. (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - III. Contributions to books: #96a - "Realidad y expresión en la literatura estridentista." In Estridentismo: Memoria y valoración. México: SEP, 1983, pp. 62-79. (see No. 467) #97 - "Realismo en Hispanoamerica." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1974 ed. #98 - "El realismo mágico y la nueva narrativa hispanoamericana." In Variaciones interpretativas en torno a la nueva narrativa hispanoamericana. Ed. Donald W. Bleznick. Santiago, Chile: Helmy F. Giacoman. 1972, pp. 49-62. #99 - "Rodolfo Usigli." Gran Enciclopedia Rialp. 1975 ed. (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - III. Contributions to books: #92 - "Prose Fiction. México." In Handbook of Latin American Studies, No. 34. Ed. Donald E.J. Steward. Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1972, pp. 446-458. #93 - "Prose Fiction. México." In Handbook of Latin AMrican Studies, No. 36. Ed. Donald E.J. Steward. Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1974, pp. 372-380. #94 - "Prose Fiction. México." In Handbook of Latin American Studies, No. 38. Ed. Dolores Moyano Martín and Donald E.J. Steward. Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1976, pp. 408-413. (Box 29, Folder 1)